All right, בוקר
טוב *Boker Tov*,
today is בכורות bechors כ"ח *Bechoros Kaf-Ches*, 28,
and we start at the very top of the page. ואידך *Ve-idach*,
it's three lines down. Basically the discussion had been that the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishnah* says that a בכור bechor *Bechor* is supposed to be
brought within the first year, or if it's a בעל מום mum,
*Ba'al Mum*, eaten within the first year. Like I said the other
day, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* spells out
very clearly that it does not mean it's פסול *pasul* after the
first year. It's not like
other animals where the animal, the requirement of the קרבן korban *korban*
is the animal be a year old. Here it's the obligation of
the owners that it be brought within the first year, which actually
leads תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* to raise the question about then isn't there
already an obligation of בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*, that you cannot postpone
bringing your obligations as קרבנות *korbanos* for a year, so doesn't that
cover you? תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says, well, there's some times where you
could have it based on the way the calendar falls out, that
בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher* is defined by three רגלים *regalim* and you
don't have three רגלים *regalim* fall within the first year of the
animal. But anyway, the important point being it's about the obligation of
the owner and not about the validity of the קרבן korban. *korban*.
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* learns it out from the פסוק *pasuk*
of שנה בשנה shana b'shana. *shanah b'shanah*. So now we are just
discussing what one another each one does with another פסוק *pasuk* because
שנה בשנה shana b'shana *shanah b'shanah* was learned out additionally to teach
you that it's eaten for two days and the intervening night.
Let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. ואידך
*Ve-idach*, one said that
you had a comparison to שלמים *Shlamim*, which is how you would
know another way you could know two days and the intervening night.
You would have said maybe it should be compared to a תודה
*Todah*. It says no, no, no, it says יהיה לך *yiheyeh lach*,
which means that you have more, extra, so clearly not just like
a תודה *Todah* of one day and a night, it's like a
שלמים *Shlamim* of two days and a night. What would the other
one say back to that? אם מהתם או הא מהתם *Im me-hasam
or ha me-hasam*, איכא למימר *ika l'meimar* האי *hai* יהיה לך *yiheyeh
lach*, no, יהיה לך *yiheyeh lach* might not have told you two
days for eating it. It might have told you למימד על בכור
bechor בעל מום mum, שנתנו לכהן *limid al bechor ba'al mum she-nosno
l'kohen*, that even when it gets a blemish you give it to
the כהן kohen *kohen*. שלא מצינו בכל התורה כולה *She-lo matzinu b'chol
ha-Torah kulah*, that we've never found it anywhere else in the תורה
*Torah*, this idea that when it has a blemish you give it
to the כהן kohen *kohen*. Therefore you needed the יהיה לך *yiheyeh
lach*. תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafos* says that phrase, שלא מצינו בכל התורה כולה
*She-lo matzinu b'chol ha-Torah kulah*, we never found it elsewhere, you could
say that phrase everywhere, anytime the פסוק *pasuk* teaches you something we
don't know from before, say we never knew it anywhere else, so
therefore it had to teach it. And the phrase seems to be
indicating that there's something more distinctive about this, something very unusual about
this that you needed a special פסוק *pasuk* to teach it. תוספות
Tosafos *Tosafos* says what is unusual is that the idea that even
with a blemish you eat it out of the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*, even without redeeming it. It retains its קדושה *kedushah*,
it has a blemish, and you eat it, you don't redeem it,
and you eat it out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis
HaMikdash*, and you still give it to the כהן kohen *kohen*. That
is highly unusual. In fact, the only other thing that's like that
is מעשר *Ma'aser*. But that is so highly unusual that with a
blemish you don't redeem it and you still eat it with its
קדושה *kedushah* out of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, that you need
a special פסוק *pasuk*. You cannot use that to tell you this
idea of two days and a night, there's much more important things
we need to first learn from that. Not important, but anyway, bigger
חידושים *chiddushim* we need to learn. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ואידך
*Ve-idach*, what would the response be? No, אמר ובשרם יהיה לך *amar
u-vesaram yiheyeh lach*, it says their flesh in the plural of the
בכור bechor *bechor* shall be to you the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*. It's
in the plural, אחד תם ואחד בעל מום mum. *echad tam v'echad
ba'al mum*, to tell you whether with a blemish or without a
blemish you the כהנים kohanim *kohanim* get it. You learn it from
the plural of ובשרם *u-vesaram* that with a blemish it's given to
the כהן kohen, *kohen* and somehow because it's a sense of they
get it, they get it as a בכור bechor *bechor* without redeeming
it. Therefore you don't need the יהיה לך *yiheyeh lach*. ואידך *Ve-idach*,
what would the response back be? ובשרם דהני בכורות דכל ישראל Yisrael
קאמר *u-vesaram de-hani bechoros d'chol Yisrael ka-mar*, ובשרם *u-vesaram* doesn't mean anything
in particular, it means all of the בכורות *bechoros* that the Jewish
people will bring you get them, but it does not mean of
two types of בכור Bechor *bechor* with or without a blemish. That
just wraps up the question about what you do with the verses,
but again the bigger point being that we have some basic points
of בכור *bechor* being taught here. Number one, it has to be
brought within the first year, that's explicit, שנה בשנה shana b'shana *shanah
b'shanah*,
but you measure it by the age of the בכור *bechor*, not
by the calendar year. And again if it's more than a year
it's still כשר *kosher*. Number two, that even with a blemish the
כהן kohen. *kohen* eats it without redeeming it out of the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. And number three, that it's eaten for two days
and the intervening night. A lot of important הלכות *halachos* of בכור
*bechor* learned from here. Now we go on to the end of
the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, which talks about what happens when it gets
a blemish, how much time, how does the clock run out in
that case? נולד לו מום nolad lo mum. *nolad lo mum*, if
it has a blemish,
hold on, we have somebody who joined us here from the group.
Yes, נולד לו מום mum *nolad lo mum*.
נולד לו מום mum. בתוך שנתו Betoch shnato. רשאי לקיימו כל שנים
עשר חודש *nolad lo mum b'soch shnaso rashai l'kaymo kol shneim asar
chodesh*. So if the בכור *bechor* gets a blemish during the first
year, although we normally said that you have a year, so here
it says you can keep it for twelve months, and then it
says, and afterwards, if you can keep it for thirty days. And
it's a little ambiguous what the משנה Mishnah means. So the גמרא
Gemara suggests two readings. So let's take a look. איבעיא להו. Ibaia
lehu. So they raised the question. היכי קאמר? Heichi ka'amar? How does
it mean? נולד לו מום בתוך שנתו ורשאי לקיימו כל י"ב חודש.
Nolad lo mum betoch shnato verashai lekaymo kol yud-bet chodesh.
If it got a blemish during the year, then you can keep
it for the twelve months. ולאחר שנתו נמי שלושים. Ule'achar shnato nami
shloshim.
And you actually have thirty months after the year. So we'll see
why would this be that you would get extra time once it's
developed a blemish. But meaning, if it develops a blemish, then you
don't just have the year, you have thirty days even after the
year. That's one way of reading the משנה. Mishnah. או דילמא. O
dilma. Or do we say, היכא דנולד בו מום בתוך שנתו ורשאי
לקיימו כל י"ב חודש. Heicha denolad bo mum betoch shnato verashai lekaymo
kol yud-bet chodesh. No,
if it gets the blemish during the year, then you're limited to
the standard one year by the time you have to either bring
the בכור as a קרבן korban. or שחט shacht it with a
blemish outside the בית המקדש. That's if it developed the blemish during
the year. ותו לא. Vetulo. And
no more. והיכא דנולד לו אחר שנתו. Veheicha denolad lo achar shnato.
Now if it got the blemish after the year, אינו רשאי לקיימו
אלא שלושים. eino rashai lekaymo ela shloshim.
Then you only have thirty days. Now that's first of all, that's
a little bit strange because if it got the blemish after the
year, as soon as the year ran out, you should have done
something with it. You should have already brought it as a קרבן.
And now it developed a blemish, and now we're going to give
you yet another thirty days. So let's take a look as the
גמרא Gemara explores this question as the reasons emerge why that might
be that the clock extends after it gets a blemish, whether during
the year or after the year. But again, the point being that
you're supposed to bring the בכור during its first year, or if
it has a מום, mum, שחט shacht it and eat it during
its first year. And now we're dealing with the משנה mishna. that
says once it gets a blemish, you get thirty days. What is
that scenario? Blemish during the year, blemish after the year? Let's take
a look. תא שמע. Ta shema. Come and hear. דתניא. Detanya. As
it was taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. בכור בזמן הזה. Bechor bazman
hazeh.
Now now it becomes clearer why the thirty days might be giving
you extra time because we're talking about nowadays. Nowadays it cannot be
brought as a קרבן. So nowadays, regardless, you have to wait for
it to develop a blemish. So you're going to wait for it
to develop a blemish, even if the year's up, you're sitting around
and waiting for it to get a blemish. So maybe after it
gets a blemish, you still have a little time to finally get
around to doing something. So let's take a look. So בכור nowadays,
עד שלא נראה להראותו לחכם, ad shelo nira lehar'oso lechacham, before it
developed a blemish and you had an opportunity to show it to
a חכם chacham who could determine whether or not it's a blemish,
רשאי לקיימו שתיים ושלוש שנים. rashai lekaymo shtayim veshalosh shanim. You have
two, three years. What are you supposed to do? You can't do
anything with it, it hasn't developed a blemish yet. Now תוספות Tosafos
says that that would be almost tautologist. If it didn't get a
blemish, of course you're allowed to keep it. What are you supposed
to do? There's no בית המקדש. So תוספות Tosafot rather says עד
שלא נראה להראותו לחכם ad shelo nira lehar'oso lechacham doesn't just mean
it doesn't have a blemish, but means that there's nobody immediately available
to look at it. And the point here is that you don't
have to run to the ends of the earth to find somebody
to look at it. You can wait two, three years, however long
it takes until somebody is able to come around who has enough
expertise. So that's important. You don't have to spend money going around
trying to get somebody to look at it. You can hold on
to it as long as it requires till A, it gets a
blemish, and till B, you find somebody who can inspect it. Now,
נולד לו מום. mum Now again, we're talking classically here it would
be the כהן kohen, that has this, although we'll see in a
minute רש"י Rashi might say that you haven't given it to the
כהן Cohen yet.
ומשנראה להראותו לחכם. umishenira lehar'oso lechacham. And once it is able to
be shown to a חכם. chacham. Again, that vindicates like תוספות, Tosafot
there's somebody who is available now. ונולד לו מום. venolad lo mum.
And it has this blemish. If it has a blemish, it's available
to be shown. So now how does your timing work? בתוך שנתו.
If it happened during the year, רשאי לקיימו כל י"ב חודש. rashai
lekaymo kol yud-bet chodesh. Then you have twelve months. אחר שנתו. Achar
shnato. After the year, אינו רשאי לקיימו אפילו יום אחד. eino rashai
lekaymo afilu yom echad. You really shouldn't even have one day. אפילו
שעה אחת. afilu sha'ah achas. Even one hour, right? Because the whole
point is that you were supposed to do it during the year.
אבל. Aval. But however, מפני השבת אבידה לבעלים, mipnei hashavas aveida leba'alim,
because of returning the lost to the owners, we'll describe what that
means in a minute, אמרו, amru, they said, רשאי לקיימו שלושים יום.
rashai lekaymo shloshim yom. That they were going to give you thirty
extra days. They really shouldn't have given you any time after the
year, but they had רחמנות rachmanus and they gave you thirty days.
Now, what is the השבת אבידה לבעלים? hashavas aveida leba'alim? So רש"י
Rashi says,
let me just read the line in רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi says that you don't have a כהן Cohen available to
give it to. And he says if you were to שחט shacht
it right away, right, you the ישראל Yisrael would have שחט shacht
it because you're told, hey, you got to שחט shacht it within
the year. So he would have שחט shacht it because if there's
no כהן, Cohen you're going to שחט shacht it because if that's
what the rabbis are saying, then what's going to happen? Then the
meat is going to rot and the כהנים are going to get
nothing. So therefore רש"י Rashi says that because we're concerned that the
כהנים won't have anything to get, then we give you an extra
thirty days to find a כהן. Cohen תוספות Tosafot says a less
radical case. תוספות Tosafot says since when are we talking that the
ישראל is still holding on to it? If you remember from the
משנה mishna, *Mishna*, the ישראל *Yisroel* was supposed to give it to
the כהן Cohen *Kohen* after like a month or two. So the
כהן *Kohen* has it. So what's the השבת אבידה hashavas aveida *Hashavas
Aveida*? The השבת אבידה *Hashavas Aveida* for תוספות *Tosfos* is a much
lower threshold. For תוספות *Tosfos* it's that sure the כהן *Kohen* can
שחט shechted *shecht* it now, but he doesn't need 30 pounds of
meat right now. So since he doesn't need 30 pounds of meat,
are we going to demand that he שחט shecht *shecht* it or
are we going to give him time to maybe line up some
potential buyers, you know, do something with it so that when he
gets around to שחטינג *shechting* it, it'll be able to dispose of
the meat in a way that it won't be a serious loss.
Okay, so that's more like a more common scenario and also shows
that we don't have such a high threshold. You know, it is
yours, you could שחט shecht *shecht* it, you could start eating it,
but we're giving you 30 days in order to make the most
out of it. So, so that's what we have. So again, what
does the ברייתא *Braisa* say? It says you're supposed to do it
within the year, but of course you've got a little problem nowadays.
You can't do anything until it gets a מום *mum*. So fine,
so until it gets a מום *mum*, until somebody's available to look
at it, you hang on to it. Once that happens, it gets
a מום *mum* and somebody's available to look on it, so then
what are you going to do? Then you have 30 days, then
you have the whole year, and after the year 30 days in
order to give yourself time to get things lined up. Now, the
question is how to read that key line: after the end of
the year 30 days. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first thinks to read
it that you get the year plus an additional 30 days, even
if the מום *mum* was developed during the year. But the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* immediately points out that the same ambiguity in the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishna* is present in the ברייתא *Braisa*. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ועדיין תיבעי לי *V'adayan tibayei
li*, I still have my same question. שלושים יום אחר שנתו *Shloshim
yom achar shnaso*, when it says at after the year you have
30 days, what's the scenario? Does it mean it got the מום
*mum* developed during the year and you have 30 days to after
the year? או דילמא *O dilma*, תיבעי לי *tibayei li*, שלושים יום
אחר שנתו *shloshim yom achar shnaso*, does maybe it means that no,
if it developed the מום *mum* after 30 days after the year,
then you have 30 days. או דילמא קודם שנתו *O dilma kodem
shnaso*, or even during the year you have an additional 30 days.
And we have to admit that the logic is much more the
former. Meaning, if you're told that you have a year, right, to
do it, and it develops the מום *mum*, I don't know, in
the first month, then why should you get not only a year,
but a year and 30 days? Right? No logic why we should
tag on 30 days just because it developed a מום *mum* during
the year. The logic is, if it got the מום *mum* during
the year, you have till the year runs out. If it developed
the מום *mum* after the year, which you had no choice but
to hold on to it till after the year, you were waiting
for the מום *mum*, so then we're not going to demand that
you do it instantaneously, we'll give you a little bit of time
and we'll give you 30 days. So that really makes the most
sense. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says the phrasing in the משנה
Mishnah *Mishna* is ambiguous and we will see a middle position that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is about to present right now. So let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: תא שמע
*Ta
shma*, come and hear. נולד לו מום בחמישה עשר יום בתוך שנתו
*Nolad lo mum b'chamisha asar yom b'toch shnaso*. It's got a blemish
with 15 days left on the year. Now this is the case
where we would understand why would we give you a little extra
time. If it got a מום *mum* on the first month, why
should we give you a year and 30 days? But if it
got a מום *mum* with 15 days left to the year, then
why should we give you only 15 days? That's giving you barely
any time. So if it got a blemish with only 15 days
left to the year, משלימין לו חמישה עשר יום אחר שנתו *mashlimin
lo chamisha asar yom achar shnaso*, you get the 15 days at
the end of the year plus an additional 15 days. So שמע
מינה shma mina *shma mina*, so that is a good proof. What
does it prove? It proves that the basic point is that you
get 30 days, I'm trying to think of the best way to
frame this, is it 30 days or to the end of the
year, whichever comes later. That's the basic principle. So if it's early
in the year, you get till the end of the year. If
it's after the year, you get 30 days. If it's with 15
days left in the year, you get 15 days plus the next
15 days. If it's 10 days left in the year, you have
10 days plus 20 days. So basically the principle is, and that's
the only thing that makes sense, why if it got on the,
you know, during the first week should you get a year and
a month? So really the principle is, if it gets a מום
*mum*, which now you have an opportunity to do something, you have
till the end of the year or till the end of the
30 days, whichever comes later. And that's the way to read it.
So basically the way you read the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* is if
it got the מום *mum* after the year, then we give you
30 days. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just wraps this
up. מסייע ליה לרבי אליעזר *Mesayei l'Rabbi Eliezer*, this supports Rabbi Eliezer.
דאמר רבי אליעזר *D'amar Rabbi Eliezer*, Rabbi Eliezer says, נותנין לו שלושים
יום משעה שנולד בו מום *notnin lo shloshim yom mishaa shenolad bo
mum*. You give 30 days from the day the blemish has developed.
Again, that means as long as if that gives you time after
the end of the year. If it's still within the year, then
you get till the end of the year. So the end of
the year or 30 days, whichever comes later. And that seems to
be exactly what Rabbi Eliezer said. איכא דאמרי *Ika d'amri*, but some
have a different version of Rabbi Eliezer, which will not be what
we just said. אמר רבי אליעזר *Amar Rabbi Eliezer*, Rabbi Eliezer says,
מניין לבכור שנולד בו מום בתוך שנתו *minayin l'bechor shenolad bo mum
b'toch shnaso*, how do you know if it got a blemish during
the year, שנותנין לו שלושים יום אחר שנתו *shenotnin lo shloshim yom
achar shnaso*, which is exactly what we were working to reject, that
if it got a מום *mum*, I don't know, on day two...
you still give it a year and thirty days. How do you
know that? דאמר
שנאמר, the verse says, לפני ה' אלהיך תאכלנו שנה בשנה, Lifnei Hashem
Elokecha tachalenu shana b'shana, the verse we've been using,
eat it before God year by year, which for us
taught that it has to be brought within its own first year.
So he's going to also be focused on this phrase שנה בשנה.
איזו הן ימים החשובים שנה, Eizu hein yamin hachashuvim shana, what,
how many days would count as a year? He means שנה בשנה
that you actually get two years to bring it in, but not
literally two years. How many days would sometimes halachically count as a
year? הוי אומר אלו שלשים יום, Hevei omer elu shloshim yom, 30
days. Sometimes we say that a month into a year, 30 days
of the year, in some ways symbolically can represent the whole year.
So he says שנה בשנה means you get to eat it over
two years. You have a year and a month because the second
month counts as a second year. So he says in principle everybody
gets a year and a month. It's not a special exception because
of השבת אבידה to help you cut your losses, to give you
a little time, no, fundamentally it's a year and a month. So
the Gemara says מיתיבי, Meiseivei, I'll ask you on this from the
Brayta. נולד בו מום בחמשה עשר יום בתוך שנתו, Nolad bo mum
b'chamisha asar yom b'toch shnaso, if
it got a blemish 15 days before the end of the year,
משלימין לו חמשה עשר יום אחר שנתו, mashlimin lo chamisha asar yom
achar shnaso, you give it 15 days after the end of the
year. So
השלמה אין, hashlama in, yes we make up the 30 days, meaning
this concept of 30 days or the end of the year whichever
comes later, so if you didn't get 30 days we make sure
that you make it up
afterwards, מיהב לא, mi-hava lo, but we don't actually give you a
whole additional 30 days. It's not 30 days plus a year, it's
a year or 30 days. תיובתא דרבי אליעזר תיובתא, Tyufta d'Rebbi Eliezer
tyufta, that is a complete contradiction to Rabbi Eliezer's second statement. So
in the end the upshot about this is that you're supposed to
bring it within a year, except right now we've got a little
bit of a problem, which is that you can't do anything with
it until it develops a blemish. So fine, you wait till it
gets a blemish. And then the question is now that it got
this blemish do I, now that I didn't have any opportunity prior,
how much time are you going to give me to get something
done with it? How much do I have to like suffer a
loss if I have to do it immediately? So there we will
now say okay you're right, in principle if it's the end of
the year you should do it immediately, the Torah wants you to
do it at the end of the year, but we are going
to give you a month in order to get you know to
arrange things so it is not a loss. So it is basically
you have till the end of the year or at least an
extra month whichever comes first. All right, so now we're going to
move on to the next Mishna. Is everybody still there?
Hello? All right, just checking, stay there.
All right, so moving on to the next Mishna. Now we really
start moving into the issue about inspecting blemishes and also you'll see
it'll lead to a fascinating digression about questions about giving rulings on
various cases and making errors in judgment and so on, or in
din I should say, court, you know, judicial errors. So let's take
a look. השוחט את הבכור ומראה מומיו. Hashocheit es habechor umareh mumov.
You shechted the bechor and then you decided to have a Chacham
inspect it, to have a sage inspect it. You assumed that it
had a blemish, you weren't a total rasha, but you did not
make sure to get it inspected beforehand. So what are we going
to do? Are we going to allow you to use the ruling
afterwards
or are we going to say no you did the wrong thing,
you shechted it before inspecting it, and therefore you're not going to
be able to eat it. So let's take a look. רבי יהודה
מתיר, Rebbi Yehuda matir, Rabbi Yehuda says it's fine if it now
was inspected and determined to be okay. רבי מאיר אומר הואיל ונשחט
שלא על פי מומחה אסור, Rebbi Meir omer ho'il v'nishchat shelo al
pi mumche asur, since you shechted it before you asked an expert
it is forbidden.
Now it says another halacha, so that's one debate, and then it
says מי שאינו מומחה שראה את הבכור ונשחט על פיו, Mi she'eino
mumche shera'ah es habechor v'nishchat al piv, let's say you were not
an expert and you inspected it and then it was slaughtered. And
then now presumably even if afterwards it was determined to be a
genuine blemish, it says הרי זה יקבר, harei zeh yikaver, bury it
regardless,
וישלם מביתו, v'yeshalem mibeiso, and you have to now compensate the owner
because of your
judicial
negligence. So because you ruled when you should not have been ruling
in that case. So we'll see in the Gemara, the Gemara assumes
that this last line, why does it say bury it? Why doesn't
it say well let's determine first of all whether it was a
blemish or not a blemish? So you could have said it means
that somebody inspected it afterwards and said it wasn't a blemish, but
then you don't have to say bury it, of course you're going
to bury it. So the Gemara assumes that this last line is
Rabbi Meir that says you know it's just like shechting it without
a ruling is shechting it without an expert ruling and therefore we're
not going to let you benefit from it, we're going to say
bury it. And if you're to blame, you weren't the owner but
you were the person who gave the ruling and you should not
have been doing that, then you have to compensate, which is going
to lead as I said into a fascinating discussion about judicial malpractice.
But let's first start with the first debate when it was shechted
before it was inspected and inspected after. Why would Rabbi Meir not
allow the inspection
after to be legitimate? Let's take a look.
אמר רבה בר בר חנה, Amar Rabba bar bar Chana, so Rabba
bar bar Chana said, בדוקין שבעין דכלי עלמא לא פליגי, bidukin shebe'ayin
d'chulei alma lo pligi, if it
is cataracts in the eye. So that type of a case, if
that was the blemish that was שחט shechting *shechted* on, nobody debates
דאסור *d'assur* that it's forbidden even if now after the שחיטה *shechita*
it was inspected and determined to be a genuine blemish. Why? מפני
שהן משתנין *mipnei shehein mishtanin* because that can change in the moment
of death or that can change maybe regularly and or maybe particularly
due to the trauma of death. And therefore even if it looks
like a blemish now, there is no way of knowing that it
was a blemish before the שחיטה *shechita*. לא נחלקו אלא במומין שבגוף
*lo nechelku ela b'mumim she'beguf*. They were only really debating blemishes on
the body, you know, that those types of things do not change
at the moment of death. And those things, the inspection afterwards will
really tell you what its state was before שחיטה *shechita*. So we
understand of course רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda*, but let's figure
out רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rebbi Meir*. דרבי מאיר מסבר *De'Rebbi Meir
misavar* רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rebbi Meir* holds גזרינן מומין שבגוף אטו
דוקין שבעין dukin sheba'ayin *gazrinan mumim she'beguf atu dokin sheba'ayin*. If we
allow you
to benefit, if we allow you to use the ruling of the
blemishes on the body, next thing you know you'll come to do
the same thing and you'll use the rulings that the sage gives
about the case of the cataracts of the eye, even though for
that it is not a legitimate ruling. And therefore we have to
protect against those cases. ורבי יהודה סבר לא גזרינן מומין שבגוף אטו
דוקין שבעין dukin sheba'ayin *Ve'Rabbi Yehuda savar lo gazrinan mumim she'beguf atu
dokin sheba'ayin*. We do not make that גזירה gezeirah, *gezeira* and we
say since in this case it was a legitimate ruling and we
can properly assess what happened before, then we can do it, we're
not concerned it'll get mixed up with the case about the cataracts
of the eye. Now I should tell you that
I've, wait, go ahead Michael.
What? What if it's to me something that's completely obvious like it
has three legs instead of four, five legs instead of
four? You don't really need a מומחה mumcheh, *mumche* for because like
any person can tell.
Okay, so that raises I think an interesting question and you could
frame that in two ways. One way you could frame that is,
is there really a need to make a גזירה gezeirah *gezeira*? And
that may be the answer still could be yes. You know, there
you could say, well, yeah, because anytime you allow any decision, you
know, to be done afterwards,
it'll lead to just doing it in all cases, even in the
more difficult cases or the דוקין שבעין dukin sheba'ayin *dokin sheba'ayin*. But
I think what you're really asking is, not do we need to
make a גזירה gezeirah *gezeira*, but in that case can't you actually
say that like everybody essentially is a מומחה mumcheh *mumche*? That it
doesn't even require a מומחה *mumche* in that case, right? So that
it's not so that who even needs to get the מומחה *mumche*
to come afterwards to look at it, right? Any layperson in that
case can make the decision themselves. I think that is a very
good question. In a way it parallels certain questions, you know, people
ask, which is like about questions about like autonomy and rabbinic authority
and questions about like, well, you know, would you need to ask
every שאלה *shayla* to a רב *rav*? And the answer is of
course not. Like a million times in your house every day you're
making questions, you're making decisions without asking a רב *rav*, like about
well what ברכה *bracha* do you make here? And I forgot יעלה
ויבוא *Ya'aleh V'Yavo*. And like okay can I do this on שבת
*Shabbos*? You know, you so there's some things that you're always making
a lot of decisions based on your own knowledge. So your question
is here too, you know, do we say every single מום *mum*
requires a מומחה *mumche* or there are some things that are so
obvious that you could be your own מומחה *mumche* for? I think
that's a very good question. You know, I don't know the answer,
but but instinctively I agree with you.
Let's see as the you know as we continue to go through
בכורות *Bechoros*, I do not remember offhand what if there's you know
if there's a clear answer on that, but I think that's a
very good point. Is there another question?
Just one small comment. One small point
that the תורה *Torah* wants to emphasize that there is a requirement
that every question an expert must testify. For example, by צרעת *Tzaraas*.
I'm sorry, one more time.
One more time.
Yes.
Right, meaning the תורה *Torah* does say when it comes to צרעת
*Tzaraas* that it has to be a כהן *kohen*. I mean I
think what's interesting about the צרעת *Tzaraas* is I think that חז"ל
*Chazal* understand it to be ritualized, that the חז"ל *Chazal* imagine that
you take a the כהן *kohen* takes a תלמיד חכם chacham? *talmid
chacham* with him who knows the הלכות *halachos* and the כהן *kohen*
does the ritual of declaring it to be צרעת *Tzaraas*. You know,
in the פשט *pshat* of the תורה *Torah*, I mean פשט *pshat*
תורה *Torah* also that the כהנים *kohanim* were the חכמים *chachamim* at
that point or these sort of you know sages that they only
sort of got developed distinct those two classes got divided off later.
So anyway, but yes, there the by צרעת *Tzaraas* the תורה *Torah*
definitely specifies the ritual of the כהן *kohen* determining it. It does
not by בכור *bechor*. So it's only you know the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* understands that it's such a difficult issue that you know a
normal lay person can't decide. So what's your point there Dov, that
therefore there should be more latitude to assume that certain cases don't
require a מומחה *mumche* is your point, correct? Yeah, I would agree,
I would agree. I would think that there should be some cases
that are so obvious they should not, but again, unless you sort
of say that they wanted to control the institution. So I'd have
to take a look, it's a very good question. Now the point
that I wanted to make is that if you explain רבי מאיר's
Rebbi Meir גזירה, gezeirah, I would've said it has nothing to do
with דוקין שבעין dukin sheba'ayin. and oh my god, if we allow
this case, next time we're going to allow the next case. I
would've said it has to do with the irresponsibility of the owner,
that if you allow somebody to, oh, you know, no harm no
foul, you שחט shechted it, you should have showed it but you
didn't and now, oh, we can check it out afterwards and everything
is okay. So next time, I'm going to go ahead and שחט
shechted it, I'm going to שחט shechted. before asking, it's just encouraging
the bad behavior. You know, and I don't understand why we have
to make it as a גזירה gezeirah, that you'll come to make
a similar ruling on דוקין שבעין dukin sheba'ayin and the thing will
have changed. Why don't we make a גזירה gezeirah that you'll just
encourage people to constantly be שחט shechted their בכורות before showing it
to a חכם? chacham Unless the answer is that that is self-regulating
because you run a serious risk because in that case if the
חכם chacham comes and says it's not a מום, then your whole
animal goes to waste and you have to bury it. So maybe
the גמרא Gemara thought that that was self-regulating and we don't have
to worry about that case. But to me, that should certainly seem
to be the most obvious problem here. You know, the language of
the משנה is חבל ונשחט שלא על פי חכם, chavel venishchat shelo
al pi chacham, that you did something wrong, you didn't do the
procedure and it's encouraging bad behavior to allow you to salvage this
situation. Anyway, that's not exactly the way the גמרא Gemara understands it.
So let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami
hachi, we taught similarly, השוחט את הבכור ומראה מומיו, hashochet et habechor
umare mummav, you שחט shachat the בכור and then you showed the
blemish, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר omer דוקין שבעין dukin sheba'ayin אסור.
assur.
When it comes to the cataracts of the eye, that I agree
that's a problem, מפני שמשתני, mipnei shemishtannei, because that changes afterwards. מומים
שבגוף mumim shebaguf מותר, muttar, but when it comes to blemishes on
the body, that's okay, מפני שאין נשתנין, mipnei she'ein nishtannin, because they
don't change and therefore of course it's and therefore you can use
the ruling afterwards. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir. אומר, omer, רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir says, אחד זה ואחד זה echad ze ve'echad ze אסור assur
מפני שמשתני. mipnei shemishtannei.
This one or that one, they're both forbidden because things change. Now
the גמרא Gemara says that sounds like literally even blemishes on the
body change. מפני שמשתני סלקא דעתך? mipnei shemishtannei salka da'atach? You really
think blemishes on the body change? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
מומים שבגוף משתני? mumim shebaguf mishtanni?
Since when do blemishes on the body change? אלא מפני המשתנין. ela
mipnei hamishtannin.
They're both forbidden because of those that do change. Since there are
some like the ones in the eyes that do change, we're going
to have to make them all forbidden so that you should not
come to confuse one category with the other. אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מתניתין נמי דיקא, matniten nami dyaka,
now on the עמוד ב, amud bet, מתניתין נמי דיקא, matniten nami
dyaka, it also can be inferred from the language of the משנה.
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir אומר, omer, חבל ונשחט שלא על פי מומחה
chavel venishchat shelo al pi mumche אסור. assur.
Since it was שחט shachat not because not on the ruling of
an expert, it's forbidden. So שמע מינה shma mina קנסא קקניס knasa
kakanis רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir You see what's bothering him is that
you did something wrong. It's not bothering him the actual fact that
the ruling might be incorrect, right? That would be if he really
thought that the blemishes on the body actually change after death, he
would have said it's אסור assur because maybe it's not a מום.
No, he said it's אסור assur because you did something wrong. So
you see it's a קנס, knas, so שמע מינה that is a
good point. But again, I would say as I said before, the
קנס, knas, a קנס knas is different than a גזירה, gezeirah right?
קנס knas is a fine because you did something wrong which seems
to be exactly the point that I was making. The way the
גמרא Gemara framed it before it was גזירה, gezeirah. that if we
allow one case, it'll come to another case. And this actually is
an important question not only in understanding רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir but
understanding how we rule, because the גמרא Gemara says, the הלכה halacha
is, הלכה כרבי מאיר בגזירותיו. halacha k'Rebbi Meir b'gezeirotav. We rule like
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, when he makes גזירות. gezeirot. But תוספות says,
but that's
בגזירותיו ולא בקנסיו. b'gezeirotav velo b'knasav. When he makes a גזירה gezeirah.
not when he makes a קנס. knas. There's a difference, right? A
גזירה gezeira is a safeguard to prevent one case leading to another.
A קנס knas is to punish somebody for doing something wrong and
not to, you know, and obviously that has a societal benefit because
it stops that bad behavior, but it's not about slipping from one
to the next. And תוספות says because the גמרא Gemara here frames
this as a קנס, knas, we don't rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir. here. Assuming that you distinguish between a קנס knas and a
גזירה. gezeira And then he discusses other cases which it's important to
understand whether רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, is making a קנס knas or
גזירה. So I think קנס knas is exactly the principle I said.
So again the גמרא Gemara. seems to be just somehow conflating it
with the point I said before that the case of the מומים
שבגוף mumim shebaguf leads to the דוקין שבעין. dukin sheba'ayin Okay so
the גמרא Gemara now goes on. איבעיא להו. iba'u lehu. They raised
the question. מפני המשתנין בכולהו משתני? mipnei hamishtannin bekula mishtanni? Are we
saying when it says that we're concerned about דוקין שבעין because those
change, are we saying all דוקין שבעין change?
או דילמא איכא דמשתני ואיכא דלא משתני. odilma ika demishtanni ve'ika delo
mishtanni. Some change and some don't change. Sometimes if the thing will
now look like a blemish and actually was a blemish even before
it was שחט. shachat So the גמרא Gemara says למאי נפקא מינה?
lemai nafkamina? What difference does it make? לכחושי סהדי. lechushei sahadi. To
contradict witnesses. אי אמרת i'amarta כולהו משתני. kula mishtanni. If you say
all דוקין שבעין change. So let's say witnesses came and said to
the חכם chacham who's looking at it, he says, well it is
a מום right now this thing in the eye, but I you
know but I don't know what it was before it was שחט
shechted and people come in They look and they say, no, that
it is exactly what it looked like before it was שחט shechted
*shechted*. And they testify to that. Can you accept their testimony? So
אי אמרת כולהו משתני *ei amarta kulhu mishtanei*, all of them change,
שקריני נינהו *shakrinei hinhu*, these are lying witnesses, you can't trust them.
We know that it can't look now exactly the way it looked
before. Which is interesting because it could have been a blemish before,
but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s point seems to be that even if
it could be a blemish before, it's not going to look exactly
the way after the שחיטה *shechita* that will affect somehow the way
it looks. And therefore, since the חכם chacham *chacham* doesn't know exactly
how it looks like, right, he has to, we need the חכם
*chacham*'s ruling, so therefore, since it can never look exactly the same
way before and after שחיטה *shechita*, you can never get an accurate
ruling from a חכם *chacham*. And if witnesses say it looked the
exact same way, you can't trust them. אי אמרת איכא דמשתני ואיכא
דלא משתני *ei amarta ika demishtanei ve'ika delo mishtanei*, if you say
sometimes they change, sometimes they don't, סמכינן עלייהו *samchinan alaihu*, then we
can trust the witnesses and then the חכם *chacham* can give his
ruling.
So מאי *mai*, what do you say? תא שמע דאמר רבה בר
בר חנה *ta shema de'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana*, רבה בר בר
חנה *Rabbah bar bar Chana* said, סח לי רבי יאשיה דמן אושא
*sach li Rabbi Yoshiya demin Osha*, רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* from אושא
*Osha* said to me, בא ואראך בדוקין שאין משתנין *bo va'arecha beduktin
she'ein mishtanin*, come, let me show you, let me show you these
cases of the cataracts, I'll show you a case where they changed.
Okay, so I'll show you exactly what they're talking about here in
this משנה *mishna*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so ואיכא *ve'ika*,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, מדקאמר ליה בא ואראך
*mideka'amar lei bo va'arecha*, let me come and show you this, מכלל
דאיכא דמשתני ואיכא דלא משתני *miklal de'ika demishtanei ve'ika delo mishtanei*, it
sounds like some change, some don't, and he found one that did
change and he wanted to bring it in as a demonstration. So
you see they don't always change. Now, of course, I don't know
exactly if that's true just because he said let me come and
show you, you know, they, you know, like, like they tell, I
remember that, that they say that the רב"ד *Ra'avad* when they were
learning הלכות שחיטה *Hilchos Shechita*, when they learned חולין *Chullin*, he actually
brought in the, you know, the innards of the, the intestines to
show the students. But of course nowadays most people can learn as
we, as we did in the דף daf *daf*, all of חולין
*Chullin* and never see the inside of a cow. So if I
said to you one day when we were learning חולין *Chullin*, let
me come, let me show you, you know, what the קרקבן *karkaban*
is, or let me show you what, you know, what, what this
intestine is, you would all be thrilled and it doesn't mean that,
that it's a special case, it just means you've never seen it
before. So it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that since
he was saying let me show it to you, it means that
it was an unusual case rather than just the fact that it
was maybe nobody had ever actually, you know, bothered to look and
to see it, and he was just showing it to them. That's
point number one. But point number two I would say, which is
fascinating, is the question here about לחושי סהדי *lachushei sahadi*. Because this
actually gets to, it's, uh, you know, it to some degree ties
in to questions about הלכה halakhic *halacha* and science. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says that since we take a position that we know, we're
stating that we know that it always changes, we will reject evidence
to the contrary. And if somebody says it didn't change, we will
reject that, rather than maybe use that to revise our own understanding
of the facts. And this actually came up again in the world
case of טרפות *treifos*, the biggest, particularly in a תשובה *teshuvah* of
the רשב"א *Rashba*, but it also already begins in the רמב"ם *Rambam*
that says, you know, let's say witnesses say a certain thing happened
and the animal was a טרפה treifah. *treifa* lived, and according to
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it's not supposed to live, so do we
use that to revise the list of טרפות *treifos*? So that's a
much larger question. But the emphasis that the רשב"א *Rashba* says is
we cannot accept these facts before we get even into will הלכה
halakhic *halacha* change, let's talk about accepting the facts. And he says
we cannot accept these facts if they run counter to the facts
as חז"ל *Chazal* said. So therefore we basically have to say the
witnesses are lying or they're mistaken and we reject their testimony. So
that is sort of an interesting approach and I think I've mentioned
to you before this really was the approach of the entire world
pre, you know, you know, before we got into like the, you
know, sort of empirical science that you sort of, that the way
things work, not just religiously, had to do with the sort of
authoritative books. So if Galen, you know, if, if Galen's book on
human says that human anatomy looks a certain way and you're dissecting
a human and it looks different, obviously you have a, a bad,
you know, sample in front of you rather than actually revising the
authoritative book. So the authority of books over empirical and direct evidence,
you know, was certainly very common throughout the ancient world. But I
think that's interesting sort of just, you know, that statement in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that reflects that approach. The other thing that's interesting
is the, uh, what do you call it, is the fact of
combining
testimony with the assessment of a חכם *chacham*. And this also comes
up a lot we're learning הלכות נדה *Hilchos Niddah* at the ישיבה
*yeshiva*, that let's say one person has the expertise and the other
person has the facts. But the expert is not directly seeing them.
Right? So the גמרא *Gemara* says that if the witnesses said yes
it was exactly the way it looked before, then you could make
your ruling. Now there at least it's a little bit better because
he's actually observing it now and you're only relying on the witnesses
to say that it didn't change. But you have other cases where
somebody will say, you know, here's exactly the way the thing looked
and the, the expert or the rabbi whatever has to make a
ruling even though he's not directly observing it. So then you can
make your ruling. Now there at least it's a little bit better,
because he's actually observing it now and you're only relying on the
witnesses to say that it didn't change. But you have other cases
where somebody will say, here's exactly the way the thing looked, and
the expert or the rabbi or whatever has to make a ruling
even though he's not directly observing it. So that and that does
raise questions about accuracy and so on. But that is also sort
of hinted to here in the גמרא, but again, not exactly the
same thing which exactly the sage is observing is directly observing it
and we're just relying on the witnesses to say no change occurred.
Okay, so that is the case about whether you can rule after
the fact and and whether we make a fine or גזירה and
now we move on to the end of it, which is somebody
who did give a ruling but the person was not was not
authorized to give a ruling, he was not really an expert. So
it says the first thing it says is you bury it, presumably
regardless of what the decision was afterwards. So the גמרא says like
this, לימא תנן leima tnan so it says מי שאינו מומחה וראה
בכור ונשחט על פיו, mi she'eino mumche vera'ah bechor venishchat al piv,
somebody who wasn't an expert and gave a ruling, הרי זה יקבר,
harei zeh yikaver, first point is bury it, nobody can benefit, presumably
even if it really was a blemish. וישלם מביתו, veyashalem mibeito, the
second point is he has to compensate. So let's first deal with
the fact that you bury it. לימא תנן סתמא כרבי מאיר, leima
tnan stama kerabi Meir, let's say our סתם stam is רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir because it says bury it regardless. So the גמרא says
no, דילמא בדוקין שבעין ודברי הכל, dilma bedukin sheba'ayin vedivrei hakol, maybe
it's the case about again the cataracts of the eye where therefore
nobody everybody agrees you cannot trust the ruling afterwards and you have
to bury it. Now I would have said that if within the
context not of גזירה but of קנס knas and trying to prevent
bad behavior, that this case actually is worse than the case where
the person שחט it without an expert. Because the person שחט it
without an expert, you know, we could say as I said that's
maybe like self-regulating, you know you're getting yourself into trouble. But if
we actually allow a case where somebody who's not an authority is
going around and giving rulings and we actually allow that even as
long as after the fact, you know, we inspected it and saw
that it was okay, you know, there's a serious danger here. The
serious danger here is that people begin to perceive him, they ignore
the fact that it needs to be verified after the fact, they
see that he's going around giving rulings and people are acting on
it and he gets to be perceived to be an authority. So
I would have suggested that this is a case that even רבי
יהודה would agree because it's just more dangerous when you have this
person who's not an authority giving rulings than when people are just
doing it on their own. Anyway, the גמרא is sort of I
think is ignoring that approach, but regardless here we are saying that
this does not have to be limited to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir
And now we turn to what is going to be the focus
of the גמרא for the next little while, which is the case
of legal malpractice. And you gave a ruling and it caused somebody
a loss and now you are the one that has to compensate.
So let's take a look. תנא, tana, we taught, כשהוא משלם, keshehu
meshalem, when you pay, משלם רביע לדקה ומחצה לגסה. meshalem revia ledaka
umchetza legasa. You don't pay the whole cost of the animal, you
pay a quarter for grazing animals and half for a cow. So
there's two questions. One question is why are you not paying the
full? And the other question is why are you not paying the
different between the cow and the sheep? The גמרא is only going
to ask the second question. Why are you not paying the full?
רש"י Rashi תוספות says because it's not really a full loss. We're
talking about nowadays, the whole point is you could only שחט it
and eat it with a מום. So it's possible that this animal
will never develop a מום, or it's possible that it'll develop a
מום only in old age and after you've invested a lot of
money in raising it and the the you know and the return
on your investment is very little. So the actual loss is not
is not necessarily the full value of the animal. So therefore it's
only going to be half. Fine, half, but why is it different
between a cow and a sheep? So let's take a look.
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר רב פפא, amar Rav
Papa, זה הפסד מרובה וזה הפסד מועט. zeh hefsed merubeh vezeh hefsed
mu'at. One of them is a great loss and the other a
little loss. Cows are a lot more than a sheep, worth a
lot more than a sheep. So the גמרא asks the obvious question,
אי הכי לפום שיעורא לשלם, ei hachi lefom shi'ura leshalem,
fine, so pay one case you pay half of a big loss
and the other case you pay half of a small loss. Just
because the absolute value is different does not explain why the proportions
should be different, why it should be a half versus a quarter.
So the גמרא says alright, אמר רב הונא בר מנוח משמיה דרב
אחא בריה דרב איקא משום גזירת מגדלי בהמה דקה נגעו בה. amar
Rav Huna bar Manoach mishmeih deRav Acha breih deRav Ika mishum gezeirat
megadlei behema daka nagu bah. You're right. It has to do with
the fact that we don't like people that raise grazing animals. In
general there was a there was a prohibition to raise grazing animals
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael anywhere near inhabited places because grazing animals
what they do is they totally eat the grass all totally to
the ground and they actually, you know, if you if you keep
them in one place for long rather than constantly moving them around,
they really do destroy the vegetation. So the there was a whole
prohibition against raising grain raising animals in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael anywhere
near settled, you know, settled land. So therefore because we basically don't
like the fact that people are having these grazing animals to begin
with, we're not going to make them be you know we're not
going to make them pay as much. Of course there's a little
bit of a problem here which is that oh, I'm sorry, so
we're not going to make the חכם pay as much, right, because
the owner lost his entire animal. Of course it's a little bit
funny because the person who is let's think a look, the person
who is paying, the person who's losing out in the end is
not the owner who did something wrong by raising the animals but
it's the כהן, right, because
the
person I
maybe I already gave it to the כהן and he שחט the
animal. So the כהן is the one that loses out.
And I'm the חכם who gave the wrong ruling, I lose out
less. So it's not really clear how this makes sense because the
one that's suffering is not the one that did anything wrong. Unless
again it's just a way to sort of show that we disapprove
of the entire institution, but it's still not exactly fair in terms
of who is suffering. That might be why רשי Rashi offers another
explanation. One minute, רשי'ס Rashi's alternate explanation is not about the prohibition
of raising animals, but it's about the fact that the כהן because
grazing animals have such a high maintenance, therefore the actual return that
the כהן would have gotten on his investment would have been much
much less because by the time it eventually did develop a blemish,
the investment in grazing animals and the return on investment is much
smaller. So that's the alternate explanation רשי Rashi offers, which I believe
is exactly to address this point. Why should the person who suffers
not be the person who got anything wrong? So according to this
explanation, the כהן is getting less, but he would have gotten less
anyway because it's a grazing animal and the return on his investment
would have been less. Yes, there's a
question?
Isn't it better because the
בכור is in חוץ לארץ? Chutz La'aretz?
Yeah, that's a good point too. Yeah, you're right, that's a very
good point too. And that's another reason maybe to avoid that interpretation
that it's in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, although you know we talk
classically in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but it is true it's in
חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. So yep, that's another good reason to not
have, to avoid that read. Okay, so let's take a look now
at the next משנה. I should by the way say, one minute,
let me just see there was a תוספות I want to mention.
No,
okay fine. All right, so let's go on. So now we get
into much, we broaden the discussion about legal
malpractice. דן את הדין זיכה את החייב וחייב את הזכאי, Dan et
hadin zika et hachayav vechiyav et hazakai,
somebody made a ruling and they said that somebody that really was
liable was exempt, זיכה, zika, did not have to pay, this is
about a civil debate, or חייב את הזכאי, chiyav et hazakai, somebody
that was exempt they said they had to pay, some civil case.
טימא את הטהור וטיהר את הטמא Time et hatahor vetiher et hatame
or he said that something was טמא tamei that really was טהור,
tahor, טהור tahor that really was טמא. tamei. מה שעשה עשוי. Mah
she'asa asuy.
What's done is done. Now that's a funny question, what's done is
done. On the one case obviously it means don't give the money
back, but what does it mean by טהור tahor and טמא? tamei?
I mean if you made a mistake then obviously you don't treat
pure grain as impure or vice versa. So we'll take a look
at that. וישלם מביתו. Viyeshalem mibeito. But since you caused the person
a loss, you have to now compensate. You should not have been
ruling. Again, the context here is that you were ruling as a
single judge and as somebody that was not authorized to rule, and
therefore you have to compensate. However, אם היה מומחה לבית דין, im
haya mumche leveis din, if you however were somebody that was an
expert of the court, and there's whole discussions in סנהדרין Sanhedrin what
that requires, does it require particularly certain licensing, does it require certain
recognition from the community, but somebody that was an expert, פטור מלשלם,
patur milishalem, you are exempt because you were doing it with a
type with, you know, with authorization.
So let's first read the גמרא and then we can sort of
try to unpack that. So here's what the גמרא says.
לימא מתניתין סתם כרבי מאיר? Leima matnitin stam k'Rabbi Meir? Let's say
our משנה, סתם משנה stam mishna is going like רבי מאיר, Rebbe
Meir. דדן דינא דגרמי? de'dan dina degarmi? Because רבי מאיר judges cases
of גרמי. garmi. What does that mean? The principle is גרמא בנזיקין
פטור. grama binizikin patur. Indirect causation in damages is exempt. There's another
important category of damages which is exempt, which is not indirect causation
but היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikar. If something is not a
visible damage. So for example, if I touch a שרץ sheretz to
your תרומה, terumah, then you can't see the טומאה, tumah, but now
the whole thing is only worth like a hundredth of what its
original value was. So are those things considered damages? I caused you
loss, but not through a what is formally defined as an act
of damage, which means a direct act resulting in some physical visible
change. So normally we say you're פטור. patur. But רבי מאיר is
identified with the position of saying there's a category between גרמא grama
and מזיק mazik which is גרמי, garmi, which literally translates as 'my
grama', but means it's some sort of much more direct causation which
you do have to pay. Now what exactly is included in גרמי
garmi is a major major discussion. The רמב"ן Ramban wrote an entire
קונטרס kuntres on גרמי garmi trying to analyze all the cases in
the גמרא. What you'd like to say is that it's a case
of more direct causation, meaning it's about on a continuum of גרמא
grama and direct action, right? גרמא grama can be many degrees removed,
but if it's very close both in terms of like intent and
physically direct, then that's closer to מזיק mazik and then you're חייב.
chayav. The problem here, the problem is that it's not always
So on the one hand that's גרמא gramma because I didn't, it
was passive, I didn't do anything. On the other hand, maybe it's
also not even visible damage because you don't see the כלאים, kilayim,
maybe you do see it, maybe you see the fact that the
vines are intertwined with the wheat. So there's one question about whether
it also applies to the category of non-visible damage, but the easier
cases are when it's indirect. So here, this is indirect. I gave
a ruling, I said, you know, ראובן Ruvein pays שמעון, Shimon, and
he went and he paid. He didn't have a choice, so he
took money out of his pocket. I can't get the money back,
so that was directly as a result of my ruling, but I
didn't physically do anything. And nevertheless, we make you pay. That sounds
like רבי מאיר. So let's see what the גמרא says. So אמר
רב אלעזר אמר רב, Amar Rav Elazar amar Rav, כגון שנטל ונתן
ביד, kegon shenatal venatan beyad, no, we can make the case that
actually to prove my point, I went ahead and I took the
hundred dollars out of ראובן's Ruvein wallet and I handed it to
שמעון. Shimon. So I really physically was מזיק mazik ראובן Ruvein because
now we're saying that he really didn't owe the money. The גמרא
says one minute. בשלמא מחייב את הזכאי, Bishlama mechayev et hazakkai, I
understand how you can describe that case when I made somebody who
was exempt liable, I took the money from ראובן Ruvein and handed
it
to שמעון, Shimon, כגון שנטל ונתן ביד, kegon shenatal venatan beyad, like
you took it from and handed it over by hand. אלא זיכה
את החייב היכי דמי? Ela zika et hachayav heichi dami? What's the
case where I said that שמעון Shimon didn't have to pay ראובן
Ruvein when he really did? So, you know, how could that be
a direct action? So the גמרא says אי דאמר ליה פטור אתה,
ei de'amar lei patur ata, if I just say, you know, you're
exempt from paying, והלא לא נטל ונתן ביד, vehalo lo natal venatan
beyad, you didn't do anything physically. So אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, כגון
שהיה לו משכון ונטלו הימנו. kegon shehaya lo mashkon unetalo heimenu. No,
what happened was was that שמעון Shimon had, you know, something of
ראובן's, Ruvein some jewelry, and which was worth the hundred dollars that
he was holding onto as collateral. And I said, you know what?
ראובן Ruvein is exempt, and to prove my point, I took the
jewelry that was the collateral out of שמעון's Shimon hands and I
handed it back to ראובן. Ruvein. And the reality was that ראובן
Ruvein wasn't exempt. So I actually have taken something that שמעון Shimon
had legal rights to and taken it away from שמעון Shimon and
gotten it out of his control and he can't get it back.
So that is a direct damage that I do and therefore I
have to pay. So now we're going to explain the other cases
of the משנה. Let's take a look. טימא את הטהור, Tima et
hatahor, so what's the case of making something טהור tahor טמא? tamei?
How do I do that directly? So it says דאגבהו שרץ, de'agbehu
sheretz, to prove my point, when I said this תרומה terumah was
טמא, tamei, I'll say, and just to prove my point, I took
a שרץ sheretz and I threw it on the תרומה terumah to
prove my point. So now I directly damaged it because it really
was טהור. tahor. How about the reverse? טיהר את הטמא, Tihar et
hatamei, something was טמא tamei and I said it was טהור. tahor.
How did I do that directly? And the other question could be
asked, what loss was occurred? I said it was טהור. tahor. That's
very nice, thank you very much. What was the loss? So the
גמרא says שערבב עם פירותיו. she'irvev im peirotav. Again, like in a
way this is funny, this also sort of shows like, you know,
compensation because here like, maybe I shouldn't be judging in order to
really, you know, maybe I have a little bit of an inferiority,
you know, sense that I really know I shouldn't be judging, so
to prove my point I do these actions to show how absolute
my decision is. So I take, so I go ahead and I
take this grain and I say, just to prove to you it's
טהור, tahor, I'm going to mix it up with the rest of
your טהור תרומה. tahor terumah. And then of course it winds up
that it's טמא. tamei. So in that type of a case, what
I've done is I've damaged all of the rest of your תרומה
terumah because now it's a mixture and you can't benefit from it,
you have to treat it all as טמא. tamei. So in that
type of a case, I have to pay the damages that I
caused. What also works out here is that it explains how the
case caused the damage. טיהר את הטמא Tihar et hatamei is the
one case that you don't even understand what damage it was caused,
right? I said something was טהור. tahor. So it creates a scenario
that it was mixed up. The other thing that it also addresses,
maybe, is the question about what does the phrase mean מה שעשה
עשוי, ma she'asa asui, what's done is done. I understand what's done
is done in a civil case, you can't now make somebody pay
the money.
But what does it mean what's done is done by טהור tahor
and טמא? tamei? So that I think raises interesting questions about the
larger issue, right, about by the way טהור tahor and טמא tamei
isn't even a civil dispute, it's more like going to somebody not
like as a בית דין, Beis Din, but going to somebody just
for a הלכה ruling. And that raises, you know, interesting questions about
once you get a ruling from a rabbi, can you go ahead
and like, you know, and get a different ruling? And you're not
allowed to, you know, once you, הבא לחכם לשאול, haba lachacham lishol,
you know, once you get one ruling you're not supposed to go
and give a different ruling, another rabbi isn't supposed to overrule it.
But it raises questions about why is that? How is that ruling
sort of like binding and effective? Now maybe again we could have
understood that in the case of טימא את הטהור. tima et hatahor.
Technically it's טהור, tahor, but the rabbi ruled that it's טמא, tamei,
so that somehow we have to treat it with that status even
though maybe, you know, another rabbi is going to, wants to overrule
him. And there's direct discussions about that in the גמרא about one
rabbi overruling another in a case of like a הלכה ruling. But
טימא את הטהור tima et hatahor doesn't make, but טיהר את הטמא
tihar et hatamei doesn't make sense. It doesn't become טהור tahor if
it's really טמא. tamei. So therefore by explaining... explaining it as this
case that you physically mixed it up, it helped also address the
issues of מה שעשה עשוי, mah she-asah asuy, what's done is done.
Now, the other thing to point out here is and this is
important in terms of the גמרא is that the גמרא says that
you know what let's wait till the next משנה about how much
was your ruling completely invalid or not. So let's take a look
at the next משנה because it'll come up there.
ומעשה בפרה שנטלה האם שלה, U-ma'aseh be-farah she-nitlah ha-em shelah, there was
a story with a cow that was missing its uterus, or maybe
it was surgically removed as we'll see in a minute, and the
question was was it a טרפה. treifah So they הביאו heviu to
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and it was שחט and they discovered the
uterus had been surgically removed and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said it's
a טרפה treifah. and he fed it to the dogs because you
know you can't benefit from a טרפה. treifah. I mean you can
benefit, excuse me, so he fed it to the dogs, could be
your dogs, but you can't eat it. ובא מעשה לפני חכמים ביבנה,
U-ba ma'aseh lifnei chachamim be-Yavneh, this case was brought in front of
the sages in Yavneh, והתירוה, ve-hitiruha, and they actually said you know
what, an animal without a uterus is not a טרפה. treifah. Why?
שאמר תודוס הרופא, She-amar Todos ha-Rofeh, this is very interesting considering earlier
in the דף we rejected the testimony of witnesses, but here we're
going by expert testimony. So
תודוס Todos the doctor says, אין פרה וחזירה יוצאת מאלכסנדריא של מצרים
שאין חותכין האם שלה בשביל שלא תלד. Ein parah ve-chazirah yotzet me-Alexandria
shel Mitzrayim she-ein chotchin ha-em shelah bishvil she-lo teled. They had very
special breeds of cows and pigs in Alexandria and they did not
want them to breed outside. They wanted to control the market, so
they would not let any of them leave without taking out the
uterus ahead of time so that they could not have children. Wasn't
there a movie Gorky Park that's about smuggling minks out of Russia
to breed them? No, do you remember? Anybody? Hello?
All right, anyway, I think there was a movie based on a
similar point that they had the corner on the market on the
very specialized animals and they didn't want anybody else breeding them. Anyway,
and nevertheless, so what does that prove? So presumably we know that
they did it and the animals survived. So therefore you see that
animals are not a טרפה. treifah Okay, so אמר רבי טרפון, Amar
Rabbi Tarfon, when רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon heard about this, he said,
חמורך טרפון, Hachamorcha Tarfon, oy, there goes my donkey, meaning now I'm
going to have to pay for having ruled that this cow was
a טרפה treifah? and that means I'm going to have to sell
my donkey, sell my car in order to pay for this ruling.
So apparently it's interesting that a donkey is worth the price of
a cow. Anyway, אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said to him, טרפון, Tarfon, shouldn't be Rabbi, he
called him Tarfon, טרפון אתה מומחה לבית דין, Tarfon, atah mumcheh le-veit
din, no, you are an expert of the court, you are somebody
that has been authorized to rule, וכל המומחה לבית דין פטור מלשלם.
ve-chol ha-mumcheh le-veit din patur mi-leshalem. Anybody that has been given authorization,
along with that authorization comes an exemption from paying. Now why is
that? You could just say that you know you have to protect
people or nobody's going to want to take the responsibility, a very
practical sort of social purpose in order to exempt them from liability.
Another possibility could also be, and this seems to be an approach
the גמרא takes, is that you know there's a question about when
you talk about malpractice about sort of negligence or not. So you
could say that somebody that has the level of מומחה, whatever that
requires in terms of licensing and recognition and expertise, if that person
makes a mistake, we're going to assume that it was not due
to negligence, that it was totally like a freak occurrence, right? I'm
sure doctors would very much like that when it comes to issues
with their malpractice insurance. If you're an expert, of course you did
not make a negligent mistake, it had to have been something freak
and it wasn't your fault. So that's another way of understanding that,
but one way or the other, you're protected if you're a מומחה
from having to pay liability. So let's see what the גמרא says.
Yeah, yeah, I mean basically, right. I mean you don't have to
get דאקטו ביסן הפטער. de-aktu beis-n hefter. I mean it's similar, but
it's a civil case. You mean if it was the first place,
if we just wanted to protect you. Yeah, then it might be
that technically you are liable. Right. Of course the other question also
has to do with this, it's might be גרמי, garmi, where's the
נשא ונתן ביד nasa ve-natan be-yad aspect of it? So although it
does say he fed it to the dogs. But yes, there is
a question, yes, the rabbis might have to sort of manipulate it
a little bit in order to exempt you. Unless you say it's
like an אונס ones argument.
And how is it that רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon didn't know the
rule?
Well,
I think he did not know about תודוס הרופא, Todos ha-Rofeh, meaning
it's not that he didn't know the rule, it's like this is
a question about knowledge of science. Like who would ever think that
an animal missing such a major internal organ, if you're not a
doctor, right, who would ever think that it would not make it
a טרפה? Right? So I think it's not as much not knowing
rules as not knowing facts.
But you know, but then again your question could be, if certainly
if I'm trying to argue lack of negligence, your question could be,
shouldn't he have done some, you know, some investigating before making the
ruling, which I agree. Saying it's lack of negligence is the harder
approach to understand why he's exempt.
Today the דיינים dayanim have no liability whatsoever. They're just, not only
monetary, just think about the בית דין beit din that allowed Chaim
Walder to. continue his activities for years because they ruled and they
found him innocent. Yeah.
No, you're absolutely correct and you know in terms of the system
in the גמרא *Gemara*, it's very, it's very different than that. There's
this one narrow case of מומחה *Mumcheh* which is a very, very
hard status to achieve and basically a lot of, you know, like
we're reading right now and it's definitely discussed in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, there's
serious cases about liability. Now some cases as we've seen are problematic
to technically get damages because it depends on questions about was there
a physical action, was there גרמי *Garmi* or not, but the basic
sense that they're held up for their responsibility is very, very clear.
You know, there's, there's only as I, as we see it, sometimes
a question about whether, whether you can actually collect damages or not.
Yeah, no, but Rivka, your point is extremely well taken. Okay, so
let's just what?
My question
was, if he's a מומחה *Mumcheh* and he's known about his exemption
from his responsibility, then you know that רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* has
to tell him that.
You're right. That's a little bit ironic too that he
has his license on the wall?
I'm sorry, what?
He has his license hanging on the wall?
Yeah, I know.
Does he not have his license?
He, well, he had his license. He didn't exactly know that it
exempted him. I mean, but it's also a little ironic. The same
רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* that was a מומחה *Mumcheh* that made this
mistake, also with all of his מומחיות *Mumchiyut* did not know that
it also exempted him from liability. So yeah, it is quite tough
in a way which might be, you know, again raises that question
that מומחה *Mumcheh* might have a little bit more to do with
being licensed than it has to do with, you know, I mean
obviously, obviously I mean רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*, there's no, you know
in terms of expertise, but it doesn't mean that he knew everything.
So it's, it does raise an interesting question about the definition of
מומחה *Mumcheh*. So let's take a look, please, let's finish the גמרא
*Gemara*.
Okay, let's finish the גמרא *Gemara*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this, ואיפוקי ליה דטעה בדבר משנה וטועה בדבר משנה חוזר *V'taipuk lei
d'ta'a b'dvar mishna v'ta'a b'dvar mishna chozer*. One minute, and this gets
back to our discussion earlier about reversal. This error was an error
not in judgment but in, and this was essentially the question one
of you were asking, but it was an error in a משנה
*Mishna*. And this is actually quite a fascinating point, which is on
the one hand one basis for exemption as I said of understanding
מומחה *Mumcheh* is that you're completely not negligent, you're אונס *Ones*. But
there's another case which is the exact opposite extreme. It was so
obvious and such a blatant error that therefore it wasn't even a
ruling. And since it wasn't even a ruling, you didn't like give
a bad ruling, what you gave can't even constitute a ruling altogether.
And that's טועה בדבר משנה *Toeh b'dvar mishna*. The גמרא *Gemara* in
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* distinguishes between טועה בדבר משנה *Toeh b'dvar mishna* and טועה
בשיקול הדעת *Toeh b'shikul hadaas*. טועה בשיקול הדעת *Toeh b'shikul hadaas* is
a judgment that actually there are good arguments on both sides and
in theory you could have gone either way. It happens to be
that the general practice is one way and you ruled the other
way. But it was a judgment error and you could have understood
how somebody could have come to it. So that was a ruling,
but a bad ruling. As opposed to דבר משנה *Dvar mishna* which
is like a blatant black-letter law that you just forgot, that actually
was considered a non-ruling at all. And ironically, that exempts you from
liability because then it was, because then it wasn't a binding ruling.
Part of the point of the previous משנה *Mishna* of מה שעשה
עשוי *Ma she'assa assui*, forget the case of mixing up and making
things טמא *Tamei*. If I took a hundred dollars from ראובן *Reuven*
and I handed it to שמעון *Shimon* or I made a ruling
and he handed it to שמעון *Shimon*, why don't we just say
oh, it was a bad ruling, שמעון *Shimon* should give it back?
Why do I make me pay? Just give the money back. And
the answer is, is because that was a ruling that while it
was not the way an expert judge would have ruled, but it
was still at the end of the day a judgment error. You
know, it's like when does the Supreme Court reverse a case of
the lower court? It's not every mistake gets reversed. And since therefore
that was within a sort of reasonable bound, therefore the ruling is
still binding, but because in the end it was the wrong ruling,
I have to pay, which is a fascinating point. That it's binding
because it was enough within bounds to be a legitimate ruling, but
because it's determined to have been a wrong, then that creates a
liability. That was what was going on in the earlier משנה *Mishna*.
Here we're saying that if it was totally, totally against black-letter law,
it wasn't a ruling at all. It's not a ruling at all,
you have no liability. What the guy, what the guy did that
he fed it to his dogs, that was him doing it, that
wasn't my ruling. We'll talk about that in a minute. Let's read
the גמרא *Gemara*'s answer. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, how do you
know it's טועה בדבר משנה *Toeh b'dvar mishna*? Because there's a משנה
*Mishna* that says in
חולין *Chullin*, question whether the משנה *Mishna* was written before or after
רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*, but there's a משנה *Mishna* in חולין *Chullin*
that says that a missing uterus, the animal is not a טריפה
*Treifah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, חדא דהאי קאמר *Chada d'hai ka'amar*,
you're right, there are two reasons he's exempt. חדא דטעה בדבר משנה
חוזר *Chada d'ta'a b'dvar mishna chozer*. Number one, if it's a mistake
of black-letter law, the whole ruling is reversed and therefore you're not
liable. ועוד אי נמי בשיקול הדעת דמומחה לבית דין אתה וכל מומחה
לבית דין פטור מלשלם *V'od ee nami b'shikul hadaas d'mumcheh l'bais din
ata v'chol
mumcheh l'bais din patur
m'lishalem*. And therefore you're exempt. Again being quite ironic that he's exempt
either because he's an expert or because it was such a blatant
error. Both extremes, both extremes. But the interesting point here as well
is, okay, that's very nice that technically speaking it wasn't a ruling.
But you still fed the thing to the dogs. So didn't you
do that wrong? You took something that was good meat and you
fed to the dogs you're a מזיק *mazik*. So רש"י *Rashi* says
it doesn't literally mean he fed it to the dogs. Based on
his ruling, the owner went and fed it to the dogs. Okay,
but still, so what difference does it make if we call it
a ruling or not? This poor poor person isn't supposed to know
משנה *Mishna*. This person thinks that you gave a good ruling. So
why is it that in one case because he followed your ruling
you're liable and the other case technically it wasn't a ruling but
he still listened to you, why aren't you equally liable there? And
that, you know, again becomes a little bit strange that if we
formally define it as a ruling then we say that that basically
led to,
caused, you know, determined that the meat would be fed to the
dogs. If it wasn't a ruling, let's say he goes to me
on the street and he says, 'Hey, what should I do with
my animal?' I say, 'It's probably a טרפה *treifa*, you should just
go ahead and throw it out.' So since that's not a formal
ruling and he goes and he does it, so I really, you
know, that's getting back to the גרמא *grama* case. It cannot be
seen like it directly came from what I said. Did one thing
lead to the next where what I said led to him to
make a decision and so on? Yes, but that's already גרמא *grama*.
But again, that's it's a little hard to understand how the formalization
of what I said as a ruling takes it out of the
גרמא *grama* category and makes it more like it directly derived from
what I said. So there's a lot of really, really fascinating issues
here between number one legal liability and exemption if you're a מומחה
*mumche*, is that based on the fact that you're licensed or that
that's based on the fact that it's an אונס *oness*? And exemption
at the other extreme which is if it's not, which is if
it's completely non-legitimate ruling, if it's a ruling but wrong it's binding
and I'm liable. If it's not a ruling at all then I
am completely not liable but there's still questions about causation. And the
final thing that I will say is the line between טועה בדבר
משנה *to'eh bidvar Mishna* and טועה בשיקול הדעת *to'eh b'shikul hada'at* and
what's considered black letter law led to a whole discussion in ראשונים
*Rishonim* in terms of what opinions and what works are binding on
us today. What sort of texts are canonized? Like a question is
are the opinions of the גאונים *Geonim*, if you go against the
גאונים *Geonim*, are you טועה בדבר משנה *to'eh bidvar Mishna*? Which really
led to the question about, you know, which types of texts and
opinions became canonized within הלכה *halacha* so that they got the quality
of טועה בדבר משנה *to'eh bidvar Mishna* and to what degree was
after let's say the משנה *Mishna* and the גמרא *Gemara* everything else
was שיקול הדעת *shikul hada'at*. Okay, so a lot to think about,
we will pick up with this tomorrow.